<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned and gracious sermon preached at Paules Crosse by that famous and iudicious diuine, Iohn Spenser ... ; published for the benefite of Christs vineyard, by H.M.</title>
            <author>Spenser, John, 1559-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22576927</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22576927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25616</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25616)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1758:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned and gracious sermon preached at Paules Crosse by that famous and iudicious diuine, Iohn Spenser ... ; published for the benefite of Christs vineyard, by H.M.</title>
                  <author>Spenser, John, 1559-1614.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, Hamlett.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by George Purslowe for Samuel Rande, and are to be solde at his shoppe neere Holborne Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: Gods love to his vineyard.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Hamlett Marshall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah V, 3-4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:1"/>
            <p>A LEARNED AND GRACIOVS SERMON Preached at Paules Croſſe, BY THAT FAMOVS AND ludicious Diuine, IOHN SPENSER, <hi>D. of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and late Preſident of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chr: Coll: in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the benefite of Chriſts Vineyard, by H. M.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IOHN 15.2.</bibl>
               <p>Euery branch that beares not fruit in me, he taketh away, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>George Purſlowe</hi> for <hi>Samuel Rande,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe neere Holborne Bridge. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVER END AND worthily honoured Father in <hi>God,</hi> IOHN <hi>by Diuine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,</hi> L. Biſhop of LONDON, <hi>Grace and Peace be multiplied, with</hi> all the complements of true <hi>Eſſentiall Happineſse.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this Heauenly Sermon, (Right Reuerend and moſt worthy <hi>Moece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> of Learning) I may iuſtly compare to <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt,</hi> of whom Ieſus giueth this commendation, that hee was a burning and a ſhining light, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.35. for hee was a
<pb facs="tcp:25616:3"/>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> indeede, a faithfull diſpenſer of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God; in whom the grace of God was exceedingly reſplendent, who burned with zeale &amp; loue towards Gods Vineyard; and was while he liued, ſuch a ſhining light in the houſe of God, in reſpect of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, learning, piety and godlineſſe, that he was reuerenced of all good men, admired of ſuch as excell in iudicious learning; yea, all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of what ſort or condition ſoeuer, which knew him, did worthily afforde him the teſtimony of a milde and louing ſpirit. Oh, what admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable height of knowledge, and depth of iudgement dwelled within the lowly minde of this true humble man, great in all mens eyes except his owne! with what grauity, &amp; maieſty of ſpeech did his tongue vtter hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly myſteries, which many a Chriſtian eare hath heard, with vnſpeakable ioy and comfort! Oh, how did he empty himſelfe to fill others! how did hee waſte and conſume himſelfe, to inlighten that flocke which was committed to his chargel yea, as it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true goodnes to communicate it ſelfe to others; ſo was it this good mans endeuor,
<pb facs="tcp:25616:3"/>that as he was <hi>Lux illuminata,</hi> inlightned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with knowledge and grace from aboue, ſo he might be <hi>Lux illuminans,</hi> the inſtrument and ſeruant of God to inlighten others in the wayes of their peace, to the glory of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt, and the ſoules health of the lambs of his little flocke. For mine owne part I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it freely, that as I was to him vnder God moſt of al indebted for my liuelihood in this world: ſo for matter of learning &amp; light of knowledge (if I haue any) it was eſpecially drawn from his fountain, &amp; deriued from the ſplendor of his goodnes; yea, while I liued as it were vnder his roofe (being his Miniſter for the ſpace of fiue yeares) what gaine I got by attending his voyce, how much I haue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by penning and obſeruing his precious meditations, and what a bleſsing I haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from the harueſt of his honeſt, religious, and vnblameable conuerſation; thoſe which knew mee before, and haue been acquainted with me ſince, can truly teſtifie to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that <hi>me mihi meliorem reddidit; quam accepit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore now to ſhew my thankfulnes in part, and the reuerend reſpect I deſeruedly
<pb facs="tcp:25616:4"/>bore him, I haue vndertaken (though vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all others) to publiſh ſuch of his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned labours as he left behind him: and which I am ſure he rather penned for his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate vſe, then with any purpoſe to haue them printed eyther before or after his death: for though by all poſsible means this bleſſed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was euer ready to manifeſt his good will to the benefite of the Church, and behoofe of poſterity; yet was hee ſo lowly in his owne eyes, ſo caſt downe in his owne conceite, and his labours of ſuch little eſteeme in his own ſight, that he held nothing he did, worthy of the worlds view, though his paines were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great in the compoſing thereof; yea this of mine owne knowledge I dare affirme, that ſuch was his humility and modeſty in that kind, that when he had taken extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary paines, together with a moſt iudicious and complete Diuine in our Church, about the compiling of a learned and profitable worke now extant, yet would hee not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to put his hand to it, though hee had a ſpeciall hand in it, and therfore it fell out, that <hi>tulitalter honores.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:4"/>
            <p>Concerning this particular Sermon, which is his fathers <hi>poſtbumus,</hi> and preſents it ſelfe in the firſt place to the world before the reſt, which by Gods grace ſhall follow after, (though of it ſelfe it deſerues allowance, and binds dependency vnto it) yet am I bolde to recommend the protection thereof to your Lordſhippe, and to intitle it to your Honours name vpon due deliberation, and diuers iuſt cauſes; as firſt, in regard of the vnthankefulnes of this inconſiderate age of ours, which is more willing to entertaine euery idle Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet and vaine toy that fond inuention can excogitate, then to embrace ſuch laudable enterpriſes which further the Kingdome of God, or perſwade the truth of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the ſonnes of men: amongſt which vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full monſters, ſome are ſuch Atheiſts and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enemies of Gods truth, that they bark at them, <hi>ſicut Cerberus in Stygio;</hi> ſome are ſuch A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians, affecters of nouelty, that they will hiſſe at them, <hi>ſicut anguis in herba,</hi> and looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquint at euery occurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that fits not their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: and there is an <hi>ignauum pecus,</hi> which them ſelues ſtand idle in the market place al the day
<pb facs="tcp:25616:5"/>long, and yet with forked tongues will they not ſpare to carpe at each monument of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in a preiudicate opinion reiect &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace their paines, who ſhall but croſſe the path of their wicked delights; wherefore I much deſired (my Honourable L.) that this worthy Sermon might find ſuch an happy Patrone as your ſelfe, being aſſured, that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnder your Honourable name, it might be ſheelded from the iniurie and enuy of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, ſuperſtitious and contentious perſons, and might find with men of ſound iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the freer acceptation, and with men of great place the grauer conſideration, and with men of all ſorts the better intertainment when it comes abroad. And further, though I know your Lordſhippe delights not to haue your name diuulged in printed papers, yet I doubt not but you will bee pleaſed to patronize this poore Orphan, and ſuffer it willingly to paſſe vnder your Honors protection, and that for it own ſake, being a diſcourſe of Gods Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, a part whereof Almighty God hath made you an happy ouerſeer: but eſpecially for his fathers ſake, whom while hee liued,
<pb facs="tcp:25616:5"/>you loued as your owne life, and tendered as that which was neereſt and deareſt vnto you: oh, how did the loadſtone of your loue euer draw him after your ſelfe! ſo that in the ſame Vniuerſity you were Students together, in the ſame houſe you were ſeruants &amp; Chaplaines together, in the ſame city you were neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Preachers together: to the ſame colledges where you were firſt Students, you were aduanced together, and I doubt not, but in the ſame kingdome (though hee be gone firſt) through Gods mercy you ſhall ſhine as ſtarres together: and therefore, ſeeing (good my Lord) he ſleepeth, but you are waking, he is in heauen, and you on earth; what part or parcell of his writings can challenge as of right, protection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any man that liues, ſaue only your ſelf, who haue ſo truely loued him in his life, and ſo redoubled your affection vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in his, ſince his death, which his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, conſtant, and truly ſorrowfull widdow with her fatherleſſe children doe finde and freely confes, powring out inceſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t praiers to almighty God for you and yours? And how can you want the bleſsings of heauen, which
<pb facs="tcp:25616:6"/>haue the widdow and fatherleſſe to intercede for you vpon earth? Oh giue mee leaue to ſay of your Lordſhip, concerning this, without ſuſpition of flattery, as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> writes of <hi>Origen</hi> in his preface before his booke vpon the Canticles, <hi>In ceteris libris omnes alios vicerit, in Cantico Canticorum ſeipſum vicit:</hi> So in other of your paynfull works you goe beyond o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but in this worke of piety you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede your ſelfe. But not to treſpaſſe too far vpon your Lordſhips patience, ſeing thus the God of mercy hath moued your heart, ſincerely to affect the Author of this Sermon, and next vnder God to regard his widdow and fatherleſſe children; let me preſume to make this ſute further vnto you, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of this the liuing Image of his ſoule, the firſt fruit of his publiſhed labours, that you being a Reuerend father of the church, would giue it your bleſsing before it goe abroad, yea that bleſsing which <hi>Iacob</hi> ſent with his ſonnes into <hi>Egypt, Gen.</hi> 43.14. God Almighty giue you mercy in the ſight of the man; in the ſight of the proud man, that you may make him humble; in the ſight of the poore man,
<pb facs="tcp:25616:6"/>that you may make him content; in the ſight of the ſtubborne man, that you may make him yeeld; in the ſight of the penitent man, that you may binde vp and powre wine and oyle into his wounds; in the ſight of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren man, that you may make him fruitfull; in the ſight of euery man, that you may touch their conſciences, and winne their ſoules; but eſpecially in the ſight of our <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> our <hi>Ieſus,</hi> who euer ſo bleſſe your Lordſhip, that your waies may bee proſperous, your ſorrowes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, your comforts manie, your vertues emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, your conſcience quiet, your life holie, your death comfortable, your election ſure, and your ſaluation certaine. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humbly deuoted, Hamlett Marſhall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25616:7"/>
            <head>GODS LOVE TO HIS VINEYARD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ESAY the 5. VERSE 2.3.</bibl>
                  <p>Now therefore, O Inhabitants of Ieruſalem, and men of Iudah, Iudge, I pray you, betweene mee and my Vineyard: What could I haue done any more to my Vineyard, which I haue not done vnto it? Why haue I looked for grapes, and it bringeth forth wilde grapes?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the beginning of mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, the ſpur and goad which driueth him to Chriſt, is the ſence of his owne imperfections, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of his owne ſinnes: Strange it is, how auerſe wee are by nature from this firſt meanes of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion: ſtrange, how blinde, how partially, how corruptly we iudge in our owne cauſes: eyther not once conſidering, or not faithfully acknowledging our own tranſgreſsions: which forceth God in the ordinary courſes of mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſometimes to deale by policies and deuiſes, and to propoſe his owne caſe to him, not as his owne, but in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, and in the perſon of others: that drawing him
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25616:8"/>from himſelfe, he might alſo draw from him an vnpartiall ſentence againſt himſelfe. Thus God dealt with <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he lay aſleepe in the ſinne of <hi>Berſhebah,</hi> and would not awake himſelfe, to conſider of his owne eſtate: that when <hi>Dauid</hi> had giuen a ſeuere ſentence againſt the rich man that ſlew the poore mans lambe, and had pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced death againſt him with an oath, <hi>As the Lord liueth, hee ſhall ſurely die:</hi> The Prophet might ſtrike him to the heart with the ſentence of his owne mouth: <hi>Thou art the man; Thus and thus haſt thou done.</hi> And (to omit the manifolde examples in Scriptures of this kind) thus doth our Prophet in this place deale with the people of <hi>Iudah:</hi> he propoſeth to them a Parable, and becauſe it ſhould bee taken vp in euery mans mouth, he ſetteth it downe in verſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a ſong, of a Vineyard, which after the infinite care &amp; coſt of the husbandman, in planting, fencing, weeding, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, pruning it, could not bee wonne to bring forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, but wild, vnwholeſom, &amp;, as the word ſignifieth, ſtinking grapes; wherin, hauing euery mans ſecret iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſuch an vnprofitable vine-yard were to bee left deſolate and neglected: hee concludeth out of this, their owne ſeueritie, againſt themſelues, Verſe 7. <hi>Surely, this Vineyard of the Lord of hoſts, is the houſe of Iſrael, the men of Iudah are his pleaſant plants, and he looked for iudgement, and behold oppreſsion, for righteouſnes, and behold a crying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt by the way for the Parable it ſelf: God hath iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it profitable thus to teach his Church ſometimes by parables; which though they be vayles and ſhadows, &amp; do hide vnder them ſpiritual myſteries, yet when they are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and vnfolded, they giue a great light to the thing which they ſhadowed, and by their ſenſible ſimilitude &amp; proportion, they breed a ſenſible conceit of things remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Now to diſcourſe of this whole Parable, time will not permit. I haue made choice of that one part onely, in which the caſe of the Vineyard is put to the iudgement of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25616:8"/>people, that is, their owne cauſe is referred to their owne arbitrement. <hi>Now therefore, O inhabitants, &amp;c. Iudge I pray you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which wordes is comprehended the ſumme of the whole. 1. The Church of Iſrael is propoſed vnder the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the Lords vineyard. 2. Is ſet downe the Lords care of prouiſion for his Vineyard: <hi>What could I haue done for my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard, which I haue not done?</hi> 3. The end of Gods care and benefites, fruits, good works, (<hi>I looked for grapes.</hi>) 4. The Churches vnthankefulnes, (<hi>It bringeth forth wilde grapes.</hi>) 5. and laſtly, the iudgement which paſſed on it, (<hi>Iudge I pray you.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the Church of Iſrael, thus figured by a vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: As there is one Creator both of heauen and earth: ſo wonderfull are the ſimilitudes and reſemblances of one order of his creatures to another, of things ſenſible, to things intelligible, whereby in earth wiſe men do beholde a ſhadow of heauen it ſelfe: but of earthly things which repreſent ſpirituall, nothing doth more liuely expreſſe the nature of the viſible Church, then doth a Vineyard. <hi>A certaine houſeholder</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour, Math. 21.) <hi>planted a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard.</hi> And Iohn the 15. <hi>I am the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine, and yee are the branches, and my Father is a husbandman.</hi> For what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty can wee finde in the one, which is not in a ſort an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the other? Both Church and Vineyard, neither of them doe, as ſelfe-ſowne things naturally ſpring and multiply out of the earth, both are to bee planted by hand and by arte. <hi>Non exſanguinibus nec ex voluntate carnis, ſed ex Deo,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> of the Church. Both Vine &amp; Church grow vp the meaneſt of all plants; they cannot beare vp themſelues without props and ſtayes: euen as the Elme is to the Vine, ſo is the ciuill ſtate vnto the Church. Both in regard of their naturall weakenes are taught to twine their armes and their branches one within an other, &amp; embrace, ſuſtaine and ſtrengthen one another, as it were, growing in one by loue; when they flouriſh, and are ſuffered to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25616:9"/>ſpread, nothing ſo enlargeth it ſelfe. As <hi>Plinie</hi> ſpeaketh of Vines: <hi>Sine modo creſcunt:</hi> So the Church ſpreadeth forth her armes from the ſea vnto the riuer, from one end of the world vnto the other. In the time of their flouriſhing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and their ſummer, no plant is ſo pleaſant, euery thing harboreth vnder their ſhadow: but when winter commeth, and the perſecutions of ſtormes take away their beauty, no plant ſtandeth ſo poore, ſo deformed, ſo contemptible to the outward eye; the rich, the noble, the worldly wiſe, like their greene leaues, doe commonly fall away. Both Vineyard and Church, both muſt bee ſtrongly fenced, els they lie open to the prey of many kinds of ſpoiles: both muſt bee pruned and kept vnder with continuall cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, els they grow out luxuriouſly, and become wilde; and as for their fruits, when they proue fruitfull, how are their weake branches laden with grapes? how doe their fruites exceed their ſtrength? how doe they bring forth their grapes in bunches, and cluſters, vnited in loue? as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh of the fruits of righteouſnes, <hi>that they are brought forth in peace of them that loue peace.</hi> And as for the kinds of their fruits, all other fruits in compariſon, are as nothing: It is the fruit of theſe two vines which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth mirth and comfort to all the world; and as the vine ſpeaketh, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9. cheriſheth the heart both of God and man. Fruits of mercy and loue, how doe they warme and cheare vp the weake hearts? fruits of Iuſtice and Equity, how doe they eaſe and relieue the oppreſſed ſoule? God &amp; Angels, and men reioyce, when theſe Vines are laden with theſe fruits. For when they are vnfruitfull, both ſorts of Vines are of all trees moſt vnprofitable, ſeruing for no vſe but for the fire.</p>
            <p>This is then the nature of Gods Church. It is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Vineyard; the roote whereof is but one, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the ſecond <hi>Adam. Other foundation</hi> (ſayeth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>can no man lay:</hi> Other Plants ſhalbe rooted out: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the multitude of beleeuers are planted, into him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25616:9"/>they grow: for all the branches of it, are of their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wilde, taken from the old ſtocke, the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> euen <hi>as many as the Lord our God ſhall call,</hi> and they are ſet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that eternall Vine, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> by ingrafting.</p>
            <p>Now, as in Grafts, though all in like manner ſtand in ſtockes, and are faſtned to them with outward bonds, yet all doe not incorporate themſelues by drawing ſappe from the root, &amp; therby growing in it, and bringing forth fruite; ſo there is an outward ingrafting into Chriſt, by outward viſible bonds of vnion, the outward profeſſion of the faith of Chriſt, and the outward Sacrament of Incorporations, the ſociety and company of which outward profeſſions, ſo viſibly ingrafted, doe make the viſible Church and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of God on earth: And with this viſible and outward ingrafting, and by meanes thereof, there is wrought an inward ingrafting and incorporating, through the inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bonds of the ſpirit alſo, in which ſome doe grow into the ſtocke, and receiue ſappe and life from the roote, euen the participation of the ſpirit of life from Chriſt, and doe bring forth fruit in him; the company of which onely doe make vp that myſticall body of Chriſt, which is to man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, becauſe the bond is inuiſible. Theſe two ſorts of grafts, howſoeuer to our eyes they ſtand alike in the ſtocke, and do ſomtimes ſeem to grow alike, yet the Apoſtle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth moſt plainely with their ſeuerall bonds alſo, Rom. 2.28. <hi>Hee is not a Iew, who is a Iew outward, neither that circumciſion which is in the fleſh: but hee is a Iew, who is a Iew within, whoſe circumciſion is of the heart, in the spirit, not in the letter, whoſe prayſe is not of men, but of God.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, both theſe ſorts, as they communicate together in the outward bonds of one profeſſion, as they viſibly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue together like one viſible body, vpon that one roote Chriſt Ieſus, on whom they al outwardly profeſſe that they depend, as on the fountaine of their ſappe and life: ſo they both together make this one viſible Vineyard, and viſible Church on earth, to which God ſpeaketh by his Prophets;
<pb facs="tcp:25616:10"/>that Vineyard which is ſometimes fruitfull, and ſomtimes bringeth forth wilde grapes. And of this viſible kind of Vineyard we are now to intreat.</p>
            <p>Our next queſtion therefore is, where that Vineyarde may bee ſeene. For in <hi>Eſayes</hi> dayes; <hi>Surely</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard of the Lord of hoſts is the houſe of Iſrael, the men of Iudah are his pleaſant plants:</hi> All the world beſides, was as a wildernes and a forreſt, the habitation of wild beaſts: this onely was the Lords Paradice placed in the middeſt of the world, and fenced in from all the world; the ſubiect of our preſent Parable. But the circumſtances of this Church doc miniſter occaſion of 3. doubts, concerning the generall nature and ſtate of Gods Church on earth, which are neceſſary to be vnfolded: firſt, ſeeing the whole church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> was at theſe times ſo generally corrupted, as well in idolatry and ſuperſtition, as in life &amp; manners; that, as it is, <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. <hi>From the crowne of the head, to the ſoale of the foot, there was nothing ſound, but wounds &amp; ſwellings, and ſores full of cerruption:</hi> A doubt ariſeth how it might be called Gods Church and Vineyard, vnles an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous, and erring. Church, notwithſtanding may bee accounted Gods Church; an adulterous wife, Gods Spouſe. 2. Seeing the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at this day was diuided, and <hi>Ephram</hi> ſeparated from <hi>Iudah,</hi> not onely in ciuil ſort, but in the forme of Religion alſo; our next doubt is then, how theſe two Churches are notwithſtanding by the Prophet counted as one: <hi>The vineyard of the Lord of hoſts is the houſe of Iſrael, though the men of Iudah be his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant plants:</hi> And ſeeing both Iudah and Samaria are now laid waſte, and the Church and Vineyard there is vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; our laſt doubt is, where the Vineyard and Church of God may now be found on earth. I will lightly touch them all; ſpeaking firſt of the place where the Church is; ſecondly, of her variable ſtate, her purity and corruption: thirdly, of her vnity, how, many particular Churches are notwithſtanding one.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:10"/>
            <p>Now for the firſt, where the Vineyard of the Lord of hoſts is. Vnhappy Iſrael, thou hadſt an eternall promiſe;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 132. ver. 14.</note> 
               <hi>This</hi> (ſaid God) <hi>is my reſt for euer, here will I dwell:</hi> but thou diddeſt thy ſelfe reiect God, and didſt caſt the LORD thy Redeemer out of his owne Vineyard: thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt with a loud cry, in the ſight of the Sunne, and in the hearing of the Gentiles proteſt, <hi>Wee will not haue this man to raigne ouer vs, wee will haue no King but Caeſar.</hi> Thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt lead him out of thy City, &amp; diddeſt crucifie him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the gate, calling for the guilt of his innocent bloud, not onely vpon thine owne head, but alſo vpon the heads of all thy poſterity. And now the Lord is riſen vp again, and is departed; the Vine is remoued, and planted elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: and as for that olde Vineyard, it is burnt, it is burnt with fire, and the wilde beaſts of the forreſt haue deuoured it vp.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the Lord will not bee without a Church on earth, without a Vineyard:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.</note> if wee demand where it is now; 1. it is euident, that ſince <hi>Iudah</hi> is for her contempt laide waſte, the Lord hath planted his Church in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of the Gentiles: ſecondly, it is as euident, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the propheſies, he hath enlarged the bounds ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and hath made it vniuerſall and Catholike, ſo that there is no City nor Nation, which will receiue that eternall roote to bee planted in it, which may not become a part of his Church and Vineyard. This appeareth by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Gods proceeding. When <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollo</hi> the Lords workmen went forth to worke, in what City ſoeuer they ſtayed, they made a Vineyard; <hi>Paul planted, Apollo watered:</hi> and by their induſtry the Lord had a new Church in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth;</hi> a Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> a Church in <hi>Galatia,</hi> in <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica,</hi> in <hi>Philippi:</hi> the other Apoſtles and Euangeliſts did the like in other Countries, planting Vineyards as farre as India: ſo that if any man would know where the Lords. Church is, wee need not ſeeke for ſecret marks and tokens: Theſe Vineyards are eaſily diſcerned from other partes of
<pb facs="tcp:25616:11"/>the earth: And yet not by their fruits; for often they bring forth wilde grapes, but by their roote that is planted in them, in what Country or place ſoeuer; that Vine which came downe from heauen is planted, whereſoeuer it is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly receiued, as the roote and ſpring of mans life and ſaluation: where there is Baptiſme to ingraft and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the new profeſſed branches, and the food of the word, and the communion of the Lords Supper, to make them encreaſe and grow, there is a Vineyard: becauſe there both is his vine, &amp; the means to make it ſpread to the Lord of hoſts, and therefore there is his eye, and care, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and protection, there he expecteth fruit: for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer God vouchſafeth to beſtow the outward grace of the knowledge of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Act. 16.9</note> and to continue the ſowing of his ſeed of life; it is an euident token that he hath ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in that place.</p>
            <p>Thus of thoſe ſeuen ſeuerall Vineyards and Churches in Aſia, with their Angels and ouerſeers, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. though one Church was purer then another, and ſome were ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, that the great LORD of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard doth threaten them with deſolation, and remouing the vine root; yet his carefull eye was ouer them all, &amp; hee that ſeemeth to bee gone into a farre Country, yet was ſeene walking in the midſt of them, and, as it were holding them in his hand. And thus to ſeeke no other marks and notes of the Church, then this preſent Parable affoordeth; what greater aſſurance can we haue to our ſelues, that the Lord hath choſen vs for a part of his Vineyard, then this, that he hath with ſuch care and long aſſiduity laboured to plant the knowledge of Chriſt crucified among vs; that he hath rayſed vp ſuch multitudes of Labourers amongſt vs, and indued them with excellent faculties and graces, and ſent them into his Vineyard to follow his ſpirituall huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry; that hee hath ſo many thouſands dayly ingrafted into him by Baptiſme; that he ſo mightily protecteth them with his defences, &amp; ſo continually feedeth them with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25616:11"/>knowledge of his word, ſo importunately calleth at their hands for the fruits of a Vineyard, and no doubt receiueth ſome? for it is impoſſible that all theſe things ſhould be in vaine, as not from God, ſeeing not ſo much as the raine and ſnow from heauen doe returne againe in vaine, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 55.10.11.</p>
            <p>The ſecond queſtion which the Vineyard moueth, is concerning the ſtate of the Lords Churches, their purity or corruptions heere on earth, whether they are alwayes cleane, and not ſometimes through the negligence of the Ouerſeers ouergrowne with weeds, or through their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate couetouſneſſe ſometimes planted among, with other plants. For firſt, the Church of <hi>Iudah,</hi> howſoeuer at this time, in the dayes of <hi>Vzziah,</hi> it held the publike profeſſion of God purely, yet was it both now ſo generally corrupted in maners, that in <hi>Eſai</hi> 1. God cryeth againſt it: <hi>Ah ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Nation, laden with iniquity, corrupt children, which haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Lord:</hi> After, in the dayes of <hi>Ahas,</hi> both Prince &amp; high Prieſt and people, euen the whole outward ſtate fell to Idolatry, and by little and little ſo corrupted their waies, that as <hi>Ezechiel</hi> chargeth her, ſhee went beyond her ſiſter <hi>Samaria</hi> in ſpirituall fornication and idolatry. And yet notwithſtanding this her vncleannes, ſhee is ſtill counted the Lords Spouſe, though a harlot alſo; and the Lords vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, though for the outward face in moſt part cleane dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated; yea, and the Lord by his Prophets wooeth her as his owne, becauſe ſhee had not abſolutely renounced his couenants; otherwiſe God had no publike &amp; viſible Church and Vineyard at all vpon the earth in thoſe dayes. Nay, I may goe further and affirme of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that though it not onely worſhipped God by calues, and after in <hi>Ahabs</hi> time, did ſet vp <hi>Baal</hi> alſo, the god of the Gentiles, and then as the Prophet chargeth them, halted between God &amp; <hi>Baal:</hi> yet the Lord, not only in this place calleth it his Vineyard, and profeſſeth, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.9. <hi>I am a Father to Iſrael, Ephraim is my firſt borne;</hi> But his mercifull preſence in the middeſt of theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25616:12"/>abominations did not clean forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that he had of his Prophets continually amongſt them, and many meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of kindnes he ſent to their ſtate, and many miraculous deliuerances he wrought for them; and after almoſt three hundred yeares Idolatry, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was for this their irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocable obſtinacy in rebellious fornication to be caſt off in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of her enemies, and yeelded vp to captiuity: yet he is as it were diſtracted within himſelf, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8. <hi>How ſhal I deliuer thee vp, O Ephraim? My heart is turned within mee: I will not (yet) execute the fiercenes of my wrath:</hi> for though <hi>Ephraim</hi> were a prodigal ſonne, yet he was counted a ſonne to his laſt being, euen till he gaue vp the ſeale of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and outward profeſſion of the name of the God of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> Can then an Idolatrous Church be counted the Lords Church? and a degenerate Vine that onely groweth vpon another roote, and bringeth forth wilde fruit of another kind, be named the Lords Vineyard? Surely, to vſe Gods owne ſimilitude, where there hath publikely paſſed a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne contract of marriage, viſibly confirmed by Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and pledges mutually deliuered and receiued, though the wife keepe not the truth of her firſt faith, but euen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly and ſhameleſly turneth away her heart after other louers; yet til there paſſeth a publike renouncing one of the other, and a bill of diuorcement giuen, and ſeparation paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhe is accounted his wife whoſe name ſhe beareth, &amp; whoſe wife ſhee publikely profeſſeth her ſelfe to be: So is betweene God and his viſible Church, both <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> notwithſtanding their fornications, ſtill kept the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profeſſion of the name of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned circumciſion, the outward ſeale and pledge both of his Couenant; both offered ſacrifices to him that brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> euen by that ſtile, though in a ſuperſtitious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: both had the law of God publikely amongſt them, &amp; his Prophets alſo: And therefore this outward foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the old league and couenant continueth ſtil; the Lord accounteth them both as his; and notwithſtanding their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25616:12"/>knowne adulteries, and their children of fornication by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gods (whom they alſo ſerued) hee intreateth them, though in anger and diſpleaſure and in threates, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in chaſticements, yet as his owne (for they were neuer denounced till they were deſtroyed) and by the benefite of that ſame outward ſociety &amp; coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in the midſt of their other abominations ſtill remayned between God and them, of the word and Sacrament many ſpirituall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren alſo were borne by them to the Lord, ſuch as thoſe 7000. were in <hi>Elias</hi> dayes, who liuing in houſe together with their illegitimate brethren, feared their father, the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſecretly mourned at the abominations of their mother; howſoeuer by liuing in ſo corrupt a houſe, they might be tainted with ſome of the corruptions of their mother, and carnall brethren. And this is the nature of the Chriſtian Church, wherof that was a figure: it is here on earth, ſubiect to alterations, and to that like generall defection and ouerrunning with weeds, which both Chriſt and the Apoſtles propheſie ſhould happen in the outward and viſible face thereof, which we ſee did happen in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> before Chriſt, though the roote and foundation of Chriſtianity ſhal neuer faile in it, and the booke of God, the ſeed of immortality, ſhall remaine in it vncorrupted; and the publike profeſſion of Chriſt, ſhall neuer be vtterly choaked for the Elects ſake, that ſhall bee from age to age of this world being borne in it; yea, though one part of the Church, whoſe preſeruation of the trueth ſhall be leſſe corrupted then an other, as <hi>Iudah</hi> was in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For the particular Churches are like Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards; ſome flouriſhing for a time, ſome barren, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their husbandmen, ſome cleaner kept, ſome ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne with thornes; ſome become wilde for want of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; yea, they are like our bodies, ſome ſound and ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, ſome more diſeaſed, ſome ſicke vnto death, and ſome vncleane and leprous, and with whom there can bee no communion.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:25616:13"/>
            <p>Thus the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> in the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paules</hi> time, was not ſo ſound as the Churches of <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> the Church of <hi>Galatia</hi> was infected with a moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous error. After, when S. <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote, the church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> had her imperfections; the other ſixe Churches were more infected, and amongſt them <hi>Laodicea</hi> was in farre worſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate then either <hi>Pergamus</hi> or <hi>Thyatira;</hi> and yet all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained the Lords Churches and Vineyards in the middeſt of their errors &amp; corruptions, becauſe they helde that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Chriſtianity, vpon which the Church is builded: <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God:</hi> For although as euery ſinne is oppoſite to theloue of God, ſo euery error alſo is oppoſite to his truth, and doe not agree together: yet by reaſon of our weake eyes and iudgements, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſagreement of truth and error, as of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and ſinne, the beſt men doe receiue ſome probable errors into the ſociety of truth, without reiecting and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning their faith of thoſe grounds which they truly hold; and therefore though euery little error in matter of faith be dangerous, and cauſeth ſome defect and mayme in our practiſe of piety, eyther in our inuocations of faith, or in our works of loue, and the more deadly, the nearer they touch the principall grounds: yet they doe not all make wounds vnto death, and kill our faith and piety, till they come to be knowne and wilfull errors, that is, to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and ſinnes of the will; for then the leaſt error is deadly, becauſe it is wilfull, and directly oppoſite to the loue of the truth of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Finally, as one Church is more or leſſe pure and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe then another, ſo wee ſee how the ſelfe ſame Churches continue not alwayes in one and the ſelfe ſame ſtate; for the Church of <hi>Iudah</hi> was ſometime religious, ſometimes i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous, ſometimes purged in part the groues and high places ſtill remaining; ſo hath euery Church in the world ſince Chriſts time vndergone great alterations and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in her firſt ages was very ſound
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25616:13"/>and pure; the Eaſterne Churches were more ouergrowne with errors in theſe latter ages ſince, as <hi>Platina</hi> obſerueth, Iohn 10. <hi>The people were cleane departed from Saint Peters ſteps;</hi> the weſt Churches haue more declined, and the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Churches, except that one error of the proceeding of the holy Ghoſt, in all other parts of faith, remaine much more pure then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and her adherents: yea <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe began a little changing of her ſelfe, when <hi>Pius</hi> the fift, acknowledging that their bookes of publike diuine ſeruice in all places were ſtuffed with vaine errors of ſuperſtitions, did caſt out ſome corruptions, and (no doubt) beſides the priuate reformations both in the iudgements and practiſe of numbers of her followers, who will not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace all her abominations, ſhe would haue proceeded fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in publike reformation, had not, beſides the loue of her priuate gaines, a reſpect of her publike credit hindred her: for by confeſſing any one error, ſhee ſeeth that ſhee ſhould giue preiudice againſt her ſelf for other her opinions, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that ſhee might erre in them alſo. Which miniſtreth an anſwere to their vaine obiections; who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of vs where our Church was for ſo many ages, till <hi>Martin Luthers</hi> dayes, in what caue of the earth it lurked? for our Church is one and the ſame which it was at the firſt planting of Chriſtianity amongſt vs; It hath alwayes had one and the ſame roote and foundation, one and the ſame Chriſt publikely profeſſed, though at the firſt more purely, afterwards more corruptly; and not by Gods mercy the ſame Chriſt more purely againe. For as the new dreſsing and weeding of a Vineyard, is not a new planting; and as the often repairing the decayes and purging of the vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Temple, was not the new founding and building of another Temple; ſo in our Church, ſince it was reformed we know no other differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from that which it was before, then ſuch as wee ſee in the Vineyard and Church of <hi>Iudah,</hi> which in the dayes of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was full of ſuperſtition, in the dayes of <hi>Ioſiah</hi> had her abominations caſt out, and the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25616:14"/>purity of Gods ſeruice reſtored according to his owne law.</p>
            <p>There were crept into our Church grauen Images, &amp; the likeneſſes of things in heauen, and things in earth; and men did bow downe and worſhippe them contrary to the law, and contrary to antiquity; for, as yet appeareth euen by the buildings and walles of our moſt ancient Churches, there was no place within the Church prouided for them. To theſe Images of dead men they did light candles, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Incenſe, and offered gifts after the cuſtome of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; the light of the Church was remoued out of the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks; and the word of God, which is the true light of the world, and lanterne to our feet, was hidden vnder an vnknowne tongue, as vnder a buſhell; that which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calleth both our milke and our meate, was taken away, and nothing was read to the peoples vnderſtanding, but the lies of their Legend; the author therof had a leaden head, &amp; a brazen forehead, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues</hi> a lerned Papiſt ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſureth them. The holy Sacraments of the church were prophaned; to the ſanctified water in baptiſme, cream was added, &amp; ſalt &amp; ſpittle, &amp; by the people receiued as parts of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; the Lords Supper was mangled; the cup of bleſſing, which is the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the bloud of Chriſt, was ſacrile giouſly remoued; &amp; the communion of the bread was turned into a priuate maſſe of dead ceremonies: Theſe and infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abominations were growne vp ſo high, that they did both draw all the fatnes from the roote, and ouerdrop and ouerſhadow the true vine, and euen called for the fickle to cut them downe: for there was not any learned deuout man amongſt themſelues in thoſe ages, who did not both bewayle the corruptions of the Church, as appeareth by them that wrote, and in particular acknowledge ſome one error of theirs or other; though now authority ſtoppeth their mouthes, and clippeth ſuch tongues; and the <hi>Indices expungatorij</hi> do raſe thoſe confeſſions out of their writings. Now the indiſpoſition therefore, eyther of the Church of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25616:14"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other neighbor Church to reform themſelus, can be no iuſt excuſe for our Church, and her ouerſeers, not to reforme her ſelfe, then it had beene for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne, becauſe <hi>Iudah</hi> ſinned, or for <hi>Iudah,</hi> becauſe of the ſinne of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> In theſe caſes of Gods ſeruice and honor, the expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of neighbours, and deſire of vnity is no allowed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: but that of <hi>Ioſuah</hi> belongeth to all gouernors, which he ſpake to all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Ioſu. 15. <hi>If it ſeeme euill in your eyes to ſerue the Lord, chuſe you this day whom you will ſerue: but I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord:</hi> and that rule of <hi>Hoſea;</hi> If <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> be ioyned vnto Idols, let him alone; and if <hi>Iſrael</hi> play the harlot, yet let not <hi>Iudah</hi> ſinne. Only our hearty prayer vnto God is, that as we do communicate in the general grounds and foundations of Chriſtianity, and ioyntly profeſſe the ſame Creede, ſo the Lord would giue them hearts to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue theſe abominations, which blocke vp the way of peace and communion between Church and Church; or if eyther for pride or couetouſnes, they will acknowledge no error, yet hee would giue them contented minds to keep to themſelues their owne corruptions, which now being caſt off by vs, would be ſo much the more loathſome to put on againe.</p>
            <p>The third doubt which the vineyard of the houſe of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> anſwereth, is the vnity of the Church, ſeeing the deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded houſes of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> not ſo much ſeuered in ſtate, as in religion, are yet by our Prophet accepted as one vineyard: for though one read of many ſeuerall Churches in the new Teſtament alſo:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.</note> yet that of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is moſt true, there be many Churches, yet but one Church; and in ſuch ſort many; yet they are all but one. Nay, in the vnity of the Church, wee muſt yet goe further, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with the ſame father, the Church is the body of Chriſt; not that which is here or there, but that which is euery where throughout the world;
<note place="margin">Pſalme 90.</note> neither that which is at this time, but euen from <hi>Abel,</hi> vnto thoſe which ſhall hereafter bee borne, and belieue in Chriſt vnto the end:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25616:15"/>the whole company of ſaints belonging to one City, which is the body of Chriſt, and whereof he is head: for this is that which the Apoſtle affirmeth of all beleeuers: <hi>Bee they Iew or Gentile, bond or free, they are al incorporate into one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, they all make one body.</hi> But this vnity is properly meant of Chriſts myſticall body and Church, which is inuiſible, of which church theſe men are no part, who are onely in <hi>Sacrament is Eccleſiae,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expoundeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; that is, of the whole body of the faithfull from <hi>Adam</hi> to the end of the world; yet notwithſtanding theſe outward viſible ſocieties of profeſſed chriſtians, in which the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant members of Chriſt, mingled with the bad, are yet in framing for eternity, theſe alſo haue a bond of vnity alſo, and though they bee many, yet are they but as one.</p>
            <p>Now the outward bonds of theſe viſible Churches are diuers: for 1. they all ſpring by propagation, from one ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall mother Church: <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which is beneath, is the mother of vs all, and from <hi>Sion</hi> came the Goſpell by propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation vnto all Nations. But this bond is not ſo ſtrong, as to tie them in one, that are ſprung from one beginning: There is a ſtronger, which this Parable of a Vine doth lay before vs: for the Vine or tree which is diuided into ſo many ſeuerall branches, ſome dying, ſome ſpringing vp; and one bough perhaps bearing ſeuerall fruits from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; what is it that maketh them all one, but their owne ſtocke and roote, on which they all vifibly grow? this is the viſible bond of the ſeuerall armes, and parts of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church; they all outwardly ioyne in that one roote Chriſt, in whom they are all viſiblie ingrafted, &amp; on whom they all make outward ſhew, that they doe ſtand and grow.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. exhorting Chriſtians to vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſetteth downe this bond, and to it addeth two other kinds, the vniformity of our faith, and articles of beliefe. There is one kinde of ingrafting, one badge of their incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, Baptiſme. <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm:</hi> i. One
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25616:15"/>King, vnder which they liue; one Law, by which they are guided; one common badge of their incorporation, which they all publikely receiue: ſo that ſeeing the Iewes, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer diſperſed amongſt al the Nations of the earth, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing without dependance vpon any one common gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and yet accounted but as one Nation, becauſe of the bond of their vnity in the publike profeſſion of the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and ſeeing they that hang on <hi>Mahomet</hi> as their Prophet onely, howſoeuer diuided both in ſects and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes amongſt themſelues, are yet in regard of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon profeſſion of <hi>Mahumetiſme,</hi> accounted but as one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Mahumetans;</hi> How much more truely doe theſe 3. bonds of profeſſing one and the ſame Lord and King, of receyuing his one and the ſame law and word of incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating themſelues into one body by Baptiſme, in which 3. the eſſence of Chriſtianity conſiſteth, make al the profeſſed chriſtians of the world of one incorporation, howſoeuer they are ſcattered in the earth, and ſcattered in place and in knowledge one of another? yea, and in ſom priuat opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo differ; for they all viſibly meete in their one roote Chriſt, and in profeſſing of faith in him. To theſe 4. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bonds the Primitiue Church added, as they might, a fift bond of communion, and mutuall ſociety, euery new created Biſhoppe and ouerſeer of any particular Church, ſending his ſynodicall letters of the profeſſion of his faith to his neighbour brethren, and they accordingly receiuing one another into the communion and fellowſhippe of loue, as appeareth by the Eccleſiaſticall ſtory. Laſtly, when the Emperor himſelf became a chriſtian, and the bonds of the Empire and of the church were in a maner all one, they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a 6. bond; the common aſſemblies of all the ouerſeers of the particular Vineyards within the Empire, in common counſell to make peace, and ſet down orders for the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and vniform gouernment of the whole. But the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which in the greatnes ſhee is growne to, ſayeth of her ſelfe, as <hi>Babylon,</hi> Reuel. 18. <hi>I am a Queene, and am no
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25616:16"/>widow, and ſhall ſee no mourning,</hi> that is, I cannot faile, would teach the world a new leſſon or article of chriſtian faith, not read in the Scripture, not thought of in the Primitiue church, not acknowledged by any ancient Father, not dremed of by any ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Biſhop of that See, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding God thundered, and was angry, when the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites asked a King, as therein reiecting God to raigne ouer them; yet now the Church cannot be vnder Chriſt and his Iudges, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was, vnleſſe ſhe haue a King, an abſolute Monarch ouer her, and that is the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome:</hi> that all who acknowledge not this doctrine, are heretiques; all that yeelde not that obedience, are ſchiſmatiques; none of the Church and body of Chriſt; all as Publicans and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and in the ſtate of damnation. A fearefull ſentence, like that of the Bramble, Iugd. 9. <hi>If you put not your truſt vnder my ſhadow, fire ſhall come out from me, and conſume the Cedars of Libanon:</hi> For if all bee ſchiſmatiques, and cut off from the Church, like branches from the Vine, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged not the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for their King: then was Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> in a damnable eſtate, who not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected <hi>Stephanus</hi> the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> in a matter of faith, but in matter and caſes of iuriſdiction alſo forced appeales to <hi>Rome,</hi> and aduiſed the Biſhops of <hi>Spaine</hi> to repeale him, whom <hi>Stephanus</hi> had reſtored to his Biſhoprick. Then was Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in a damnable eſtate, who with 216. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, in the 6. Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> not onely wrote to <hi>Innocentius,</hi> not to receiue appeales out of <hi>Africa,</hi> nor to ſend his Legats a letter, nor to bring in the ſmoaky pride of the world into the Church of God, but alſo made a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree purpoſely againſt his challenged authority, that what Prieſt or Deacon ſoeuer ſhould appeale to any beyond the ſea, he ſhould be excommunicated throughout all <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what doe I ſpeake of particular Biſhoppes, that a canonicall Councell of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> of 630. Catholique Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes was in a damnable ſtate, which made a decree, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25616:16"/>the Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſhould haue equall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges with the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that he hauing the next place of honour, ſhould in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical be aduanced as farre as the See of <hi>Rome?</hi> And although the Popes Legates did by all meanes labour to ſtay the decree, as being repugnant to a former decree of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Councell for the church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> yet it paſſed with generall conſent, and was pronounced by the Iudge as the decree of the Councell: neither is this it ſelfe ſo much to be regarded, as the reaſon they gaue for that their decree; that as their Father had not giuen, without good aduice, to the See of elder <hi>Rome,</hi> the firſt place of honor, becauſe that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was the ſeat of the Empire, ſo with a former councell of 150. Biſhops at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> vnder <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the elder, moued with like conſideration, had giuen equall priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the moſt holy See of new <hi>Rome;</hi> and they inſiſting in the ſteppes of ſacred Fathers, did againe decree the ſame thing. This was in thoſe dayes the opinion of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of the whole world, concerning the ground &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Biſhoppe of <hi>Romes</hi> Primacy; neither was that the opinion of the Church for a time: but three partes of the Chriſtian world, vnder the three Patriarkes of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> haue alwayes ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued him as hereticall for his claime, inſomuch that they denied their Emperor <hi>Michael Palaeologus</hi> chriſtian burial, for yeelding to the Church in the councell at <hi>Lions;</hi> &amp; euen at this day, though their miſerable ſlauery vnder the Turke might force them to yeeld a ſhew of ſubiection to any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, of whom they might hope of any comfort: yet they cannot in their conſciences frame themſelues to this groſſe and lying flattery. Wretched men, if vndergoing ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries vnder the hands of their enemies for Chriſts name, neglecting ſuch liberties and worldly preferments, as are propoſed to reuolters, they are notwithſtanding in the damnable eſtate of the Turkes and Infidels, and Aliens from CHRIST for that default, though they thus
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25616:17"/>liue as Confeſſors, and many of them die as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
            <p>But to conclude, the vniuerſall Church and Spouſe of Chriſt, for many ages after her Lords aſcenſion, kept her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe free from theſe domeſticall yoakes; neither could ſhee bee induced, that any decree or cannon ſhould be impoſed ouer her by any one of her Biſhops, but that which her ſelf in the free and common Councel of her elder children con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to bee good for her ſelfe and hers: for execution of which orders and Canons, though ſhee appointed her elder ſonnes to ouerſee her younger firſt, ſome as Biſhoppes to ouerſee her Presbyters; and after ſome as Primates to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee her Biſhops; and laſtly, ſome as Archbiſhoppes and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks to ouerſee her Primates; yet all the orders which they exacted of particular perſons, were the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of their Synods. Now wonderfull it is to conſider, how one of her owne children, by getting the elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers place, hath in the abſence of the Lord, vſurped and claimed ouer the necks, firſt, of all his brethren in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; and laſtly, ouer the necke of his mother alſo, creeping vp by the Emperour, like Iuie by the Oke, till he had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topped him alſo; from a primacy, to a ſupremacy, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to an abſolute and viſible Monarchie and Kingdome of Romans, and as Lord of all, impoſed lawes to his owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; drawing all power into his hands, and making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as the Sunne, from which all others, both Moone and Stars do receiue their light.</p>
            <p>Thus hath <hi>Lucifer</hi> inuaded Chriſts poore Family, and hath made choyce of a perſon of humility, by whom, vnder the colour of piety and religion, hee might bring into the Church of Chriſt, the higheſt degree of pride, that euer the world ſaw in any worldly ſtate, or the weakeneſſe of man is capable of; whom hee ſetting vp on the foundation, not of a rocke, but of imagination and opinion only; and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with a triple crowne, hath perſwaded both him to take, and perſwaded men to giue more then humane ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25616:17"/>as high as to the titles of <hi>Optimus maximus,</hi> our Lord God the Pope; and as our Countryman <hi>Stapleton</hi> writeth to him, <hi>Supremum in terris Numen,</hi> forcing the Emperors ſometimes acknowledged for his gracious Lords and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes, to yeeld their neckes for him to trample on, and the Kings and Princes of the earth to licke the duſt of his feet, and all the people for their ſaluation to fall downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, as hauing all keyes and powers of heauen and earth, and hell, and purgatory; as blaſting with the breath of his mouth like lightning, whatſoeuer hee curſeth; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the oracles of God in his breaſt, and that neuer ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary priuiledge that he cannot erre.</p>
            <p>This was the puniſhment of the Church, after that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row abundance and wealth, and eaſe, ſhe became wanton, and loued not the truth: that as it was propheſied, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>God ſhould ſend ſtrong deluſions, and men ſhould belieue lies,</hi> to the aſtoniſhment of all other churches, both Eaſterne and Southerne, who wonder that wee can belieue ſuch fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>As for the neceſſity of one viſible Monarch to make the viſible church one, ſeeing the Apoſtles writings in their ſo often mention of the church, and the paſtors of the ſame, neuer intimate this doctrine of this Monarchie, ſeeing <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. the Apoſtle of purpoſe laieth the grounds of vnity, alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth thoſe other bonds, <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme,</hi> and omitteth this; ſeeing after reckoning vpon the ſeuerall degrees of Miniſters both ordinary and inordinary, giuen to his church, after his affection for the building of it in truth and loue, hee ſetteth downe Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors &amp; Teachers, this one Monarch is not once named to the church; ſeeing before Chriſts comming God had a viſible Church in <hi>Iob</hi> his houſe, not depending vpon the Church of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and is alſo granted by <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and yet the Church of God was alwayes one; ſeeing ſince Chriſt the Primitiue Church had no ſuch head, but as <hi>Aeneas Siluius</hi> acknowledgeth, <hi>Ante Nicenum Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25616:18"/>ſibi quiſque viuebat, &amp; ad Romanam Eccleſiam paruus ad modum respectus habebat:</hi> and yet in the long time of that little regard of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Church of Chriſt was one; ſeeing to this day all Churches in the three partes of the world, haue ſo anciently renounced this one head, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding may not be accounted caſtawayes, and no partes of Chriſts Church; ſeeing whatſoeuer reaſon is vrged of neceſſity, one Biſhoppe doth as neceſſarily proue the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of one King ouer all the Chriſtian world; truely, we are ſo farre from thinking the neceſſity of one viſible head to be an article of our faith, that contrariwiſe wee agree in iudgement with <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, concerning the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the ſame, who diſputing againſt the very name and title of an vniuerſal Biſhoppe, bringeth this reaſon againſt the thing, <hi>Eccleſiae vniuerſa corruit, ſi ille vniuerſus cadit:</hi> if that vniuerſall Biſhoppe ſhould fall, his fall be the ruine of the whole Church. This our lamentable experience hath made good, not onely in the gouernment of the Weſtern Churches, in which he hath been like a wilde Bore in the Lords Vineyard, but alſo in their faith, which by reaſon of their generall ſubiection to that one head, was as general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tainted with the ſame errors: for as when one foot ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, the other may ſtand and vphold the body, vnleſſe it bee carried with the ſway of that which ſlipped: ſo when one Church faileth in any point of truth, an other may ſtand &amp; vphold the ſame, vnles they be dependant one v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon an other, &amp; reſpect not that only vncorruptible head Chriſt, and his vnchangeable lawes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Now, that we haue found out the Lords Vineyard, and conſidered the nature and ſtate of the ſame, wee are in the next place to conſider the husbandry which the Lord of this Vineyard vſeth, the labour, the coſt, the skill, and care hee beſtoweth on it to make it proſper; for ſince that vniuerſall curſe pronounced by the mouth of God, <hi>Curſed be the earth for mans ſake: thornes and thiſtles ſhall it bring forth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> good things do hardly thriue, without skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25616:18"/>and Induſtrious planting and cheriſhing; their impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments are many; their helpes muſt be ſo many, that the Vineyard which is neglected and left to it ſelfe, may ſeem in a manner blameleſſe, though it proue not fruitfull; for theſe duties therefore of the husbandman, the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to himſelfe of his own goodneſſe towards it, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not to make the Vineyard and Church it ſelfe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery plant thereof, euen all the inhabitants of <hi>Iudah,</hi> his Iudges, what one thing hee hath omitted which might haue ſmothered it, <hi>(What could I haue done to my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard</hi> (ſaieth God) <hi>which I haue not done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The particulars were ſet downe before. 1. The choice of the ſeat of <hi>Canaan, (My beloued had a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard on a verie fruitfull hill.</hi> 2. His fencing it from ſpoyles (<hi>He hedged it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout</hi>) with his mighty protection. 3. The choyce of the plants, (<hi>Hee planted it with the beſt plants</hi>) the roote the (<hi>true <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine that came downe from heauen</hi>) the branches, the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham.</hi> 4. The preparing of the Soile, he gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp the ſtones that might hinder the growth, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanites and Hittites. 5. For a further defence hee built a Towre in the middeſt of it, his glorious Temple. 6. He ſet vp a Vinepreſſe in it, an Altar vpon which they might offer the fruits of their free will offerings; to thoſe hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded continuall pruning and dreſſing; &amp; watring of it from the cloudes of heauen: It appeareth after, Ver. 6. For the proofe of theſe particulars, reade the old Teſtament. What is the whole hiſtory of the Bible, but the narration of Gods bleſſings vpon his owne people, as if hee minded no other nation, no part of his creation but onely them? What is Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis, but the miraculous preſeruation of them in their firſt ſpring and tender beginnings, till they were growne into a great people, now a plant able to bee remoued, and to ſtand by it ſelfe? What are Exodus and Numbers, but a powerfull tranſlating of this Vine by a mighty hand out of the Garden of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where it was borne downe, and the gracious ordering and preſeruing of it, as it were, aboue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25616:19"/>ground in a wilderneſſe, where it had nothing to liue on for forty yeares, till it was to be planted in <hi>Canaan?</hi> What are Leuiticus and Deuternomy, but the heauenly rules and orders of husbandring, diſpoſing and pruning, and dreſſing this vine to preſerue it in ſtate? And laſtly, what are the hiſtories of <hi>Ioſua</hi> and <hi>Iudges,</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> but the mighty planting of it in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the caſting out of the Cananits, like ſtones &amp; thorns, &amp; the weeding out of thoſe mighty Nations, which might hinder the growth of the Vine? There the heauens and the earth, the ſunne, the fire, the cloudes, and the ſea, together with the Angels &amp; hoſt of heauen, all were commanded in their ſeuerall callings to attend vpon this Vine: for they were the people which the Lord called to be a holy generation, his royall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and that was the place of which he propheſieth, Pſal. 132. <hi>The Lord hath choſen Sion, and loueth to dwell in it, ſaying, here is my reſt for euer, here will I dwell, for I haue delighted ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: I will ſurely bleſſe her victuals, &amp; ſatiſfie her poore with bread: I will cloath her Priests with ſaluation, and her Saints ſhall ſhout for ioy.</hi> Now thoſe temporall bleſſings of peace and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, thoſe temporary deliuerances from al enemies, thoſe miracles and thoſe wonders, and that ſenſible preſence of God himſelfe in the middeſt of them, though they ſeeme ſtrange in our eyes, and at the reading of them doe make vs Chriſtians to ſay, Hee hath not dealte ſo with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nation, Hee hath not dealt ſo with any Chriſtian Church; yet wee are deceiued, for the gracious kindnes of God died not with <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but rather thoſe viſible mercies towards <hi>Iudah,</hi> were the viſible ſeales of his inuiſible and perpetual graces towards his Church, and euery part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for where he hath an outward Church, there he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſome elect to bee placed in it for eternity; and where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his elect are, there are all things neceſſary to their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, his <hi>Ministers, his Word, his Sacraments, his Graces, his Protection, his exceeding loue.</hi> For ſeeing thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward viſible Churches, bee as it were the Lords Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25616:19"/>wherein hee frameth the inuiſible members of Chriſts body by grace, and proportioneth them to glory: that etern all wiſdome and loue will ſo prouide, order, and proportion alſo thoſe means one to another, and all vnto the end, that it may iuſtly challenge the whole world: what ſhould I ſay? (<hi>What could I haue done for my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard which I haue not done?</hi>) And here, though occaſion is offered, It were a good thing to prayſe the Lord, and to ſing vnto the name of the moſt high, to declare this his louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the morning, and his truth all the day vntill night ſeaſon: (for ſo much of our life is Angelicall, as is ſpent in ſongs of thankefulnes vnto our God;) yet I muſt leaue this work to be the ſacrifice of your priuate deuotion. In which that one onelie benefit vpon the Chriſtian Church is more then wee ſhall be able to comprehend, that this Vineyard, this Paradice whereof himſelfe vouchſafeth to be the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, hee hath purchaſed to himſelfe by the price of bloud, not as <hi>Ahab</hi> purchaſed <hi>Naboth</hi> his Vineyard by the cruell ſhedding of the right owners bloud, and vniuſt rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the poſſeſſor of it, but by giuing an infinit price for it, the bloud of his onely beloued ſonne to redeeme it, where it lay ingaged in the hand of iuſtice: and the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth neceſſarily, Rom. 9. <hi>Hee who spared not his owne ſonne, but gaue him for his Church,</hi> how ſhall hee not with him giue all things to her? he that hath yeelded vp the perſon of his infinitly beloued to be a ſacrifice for her ſins, and doth giue his fleſh to feede his Church, and his bloud to bee her drinke: how iuſtly may hee demaund, What could he doe more for his Vineyard which hee hath not done?</p>
            <p>But here though it be with the conſent of all tongues acknowledged, that the bleſſings of God vpon his Church and euery part thereof are exceeding great, yet this chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging, as it were, of his own omnipotency, (<hi>What could I haue done more, which I haue not done?</hi>) rayſeth a doubt not to bee ouerpaſſed. For might not this houſe of <hi>Iudah</hi> &amp;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25616:20"/>the inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> haue replyed in the wordes of the Leper, Math. 8.2. <hi>Lord if thou wilt, thou canſt make me cleane?</hi> the ordinarie obiection which many godles perſons in our times doe frame, both againſt God and themſelues, attributing their impenitency not to their owne obſtinacy and corruptions, but to Gods vnreſiſtable will: for, if hee would (ſay they) he could ſanctifie vs, and make vs cleane alſo. Wherein, firſt, that is vndoubtedly true, that God, who made Iron to ſwimme, and rockes of ſtone to yeelde forth ſtreames of water; who made <hi>Aaron</hi> his dried ſtaffe to bud, and bring forth Almonds in a night; he, who could of ſtones raiſe vp children vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> if hee would by miracle, could mollifie theſe obſtinate ſinners alſo, and make their rockie hearts guſh forth with teares; hee could make them of ſtones children, and of withered ſtickes fruitfull trees, and that in a moment by the might of his omnipotent power: but as in the gouernement of the world, hee hath ſet downe an ordinary courſe according to the nature of his creatures, which he doth not alter, but vpon ſpeciall occaſion, as our Sauiour noteth in the cure of <hi>Naaman,</hi> and in the feeding of the widdow of <hi>Sarepththa,</hi> Luke 4.27. ſo in the ordering of his Church alſo, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the ſoules of men, he hath ſet down an ordinary courſe of ſecondary ſpiritual cauſes agreeable to their end, and fitted to perſwade the mind of man; as principally, the word of truth and light in the mouth of his meſſengers, accompanied with a meaſure of his ſpirit. Thus by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets hee conuerteth ſinners: if men will not heare them, no though a man ſhould riſe from the dead, ſaith our Sauiour, they will not belieue: for theſe are ſo forceable, and ſo proportionated in his wiſdom to the heart of man, ſo ſeconded with the graces of his powerfull ſpirit, both for the inſtructing of the mind, and thereby the inclining of the will, that vnleſſe a man hath more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily corrupted himſelfe in ſin, vnleſſe he be like theſe trees in <hi>Iude</hi> his Epiſtle, <hi>Twice dead,</hi> and plucked vp by the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25616:20"/>rootes, vnles hee bee like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> not onely dead, but ſtinking alſo in his graue, habitually corrupted, and that with ſuch kinds of particular vices, as are oppoſite to the receiuing of the life of grace; it could not but draw him vnto God. Of this ſort are thoſe obdurate ſinners, which <hi>haue hearts and cannot repent:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> for though all inherent ſinne be contrary to God and his truth; yet ſome ſinnes and vices are more oppoſite to Chriſt then others, which maketh ſome ſinners conuerſion more difficult then others. Thus our Sauiour affirmeth, that Publicans and Harlots ſhal ſooner come to Gods Kingdome, then proud Phariſies, that ſtand vpon their owne righteouſnes according to the Law, and therefore conceiued no need of repentance and redemption by an other Sauiour. Thus he generally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth of the Iewes, whoſe eares and hearts were by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome growne more then as all men naturally are, ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately hardned in contempt, againſt the word of truth, that,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.21</note> 
               <hi>had the ſignes and wonders that were done amongſt them beene done in Tyre and Sydon, nay in Sodom,</hi> they would haue repented in Sackcloth and Aſhes, as the Nineuites did at the preaching of <hi>Ionas</hi> onely. And this is that obſtinate oppoſition of ſome againſt the ordinary meanes of mans ſaluation, that cauſed not onely the Prophets to mourn, but our Sauiour Chriſt to ſit down and to weepe ouer <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> when he ſaw that ſhee would not bee gathered to her Redeemet; as if Chriſt ſhould haue ſaid, as God by our Prophet: <hi>What could I haue done more for my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard which I haue not done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 After the conſideration of this ſo exceeding great coſt and care beſtowed vpon the Lords Vineyard, wee are in the third place to looke vnto the end of theſe his labours and husbandry beſtowed on his Church; &amp; that is the ſame which euery man which pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth a vineyard, doth expect of his plants, <hi>fruits, (I looked for grapes)</hi> fruites natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and proper to a Vine, proper to a Chriſtian that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the nature, the ſappe, the ſpirit of the roote Chriſt.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25616:21"/>Why the good workes and fruites of Chriſtians are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to grapes, and themſelues to vines, I partly ſhewed before. For, as nothing is created for it ſelfe; ſo the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt creature that GOD hath made, is inabled with ſome gift to imitate the bounty and goodneſſe of the Creator, and to yeeld ſomthing from it ſelfe to the vſe and benefit of others; and this is their naturall worke: thus the Sun and Moone, and Starres, as they are indued with light &amp; vertue, ſo they reſtleſly moue to impart their light and influence to the inlightning and quickning of the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our world. Thus doe the cloudes flie vp and downe, emptying themſelues to inrich the earth, of which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they reape no harueſt. Thus doth the earth without reſpect of her priuate profit, liberally yeelde her riches and fatnes to the innumerable armies of creatures, which all ſucke her breſts, and hang on her for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as on their common mother: and not to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Parable, thus doe all fruit-bearing trees, ſpend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and the principall part of their ſappe and moiſture, not on the increaſe of themſelues, but in making ſome pleaſant fruit or berry, of which neyther they, nor their young ſprings ſhall taſte; and this when it is ripe &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, they voluntarily let fall at their maſters feet: &amp; thus neither doth the Vine make her ſelfe drunke with her owne grapes, nor the Oliue annoint her ſelfe with her own oyle, and yet they ſtriue to abound with fruites. For the more euery thing furthereth the common good of the world, the higher is the excellency of the nature thereof, and the greater reſemblance it hath to the Creators good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Now when heauen and earth are fruitfull in their kinde, when neyther beaſt nor tree are idle, but are alwaies bringing forth ſomething to the good of others; when not onely the creatures vnder man, but the bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of heauen are miniſtring ſpirites, perpetually and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie ſeruing for our good: when God the father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with the Lord our King, are yet working, and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25616:21"/>the ſtreames of their goodneſſe to the beſt behoofe of the world; how can it bee allowable, that when all the Armies of heauen and earth, the Creator with the creatures are thus buſied in bringing forth fruit: onely man ſhould remaine vnfruitfull, his faculties and graces idle, himſelfe a burthen to the earth? It cannot be, for not onely the Church of God, for the gathering of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; the propagation of truth and piety amongſt them, but the world it ſelfe, for the vpholding of her eſtate, doth neceſſarily require mans fruits: for ſeeing we grow toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as members in a body, and branches in a tree; the life and ſappe, &amp; ſtrength and helpe of the root, and head can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deriued to vs, vnleſſe it be conuaied by ioynts and by ſinewes, by armes and by boughes, by the mutuall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of man, by the works of iuſtice and mercy from one to another: and therefore vnleſſe the Paſtor yeelde the fruit of his light and knowledge, vnleſſe the Magiſtrate do yeelde the fruit of his iuſtice and authority, vnleſſe euery priuate man doe yeeld forth the fruite of thoſe faculties &amp; graces which they receiue not for themſelues, but for the good of the body: they are no parts of Chriſts body, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue they the ſpirit of the head, the ſpirite of loue in them; but they are theeues and murtherers, enemies to Chriſt and to his Church, they ſtarue his body, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loine from their fellow members thoſe good things which the mercifull head hath ſo intended by them to vs, that the benefite might be ours, and the thanks theirs, and al might grow by the naturall fruits of loue.</p>
            <p>But here ordinarily ariſeth in the mind of man a vaine ſhift which much hindreth his fruitfulnes, and maketh him draw in all to himſelfe, and recall his ſappe from the fruits into the roote againe, and that is a falſe reaſoning with himſelfe, that becauſe, doe he the beſt he can, yet his fruits will bee earthly and ſowre, and neuer perfect and kindely ripened, becauſe were they neuer ſo perfect and abundant, yet they cannot merite lifes eternity to him that beareth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25616:22"/>them, and becauſe that which is wanting, is fully ſupplied in the all-ſufficient fulneſſe and ſuperrogatiue merits of the head, and therefore it is but loſt labour to ſpend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in bringing forth ſuch vnperfect fruites, ſo helpeles in the worke of his owne ſaluation: thus doth iniquity lie vnto her ſelfe, and turneth the truth of God into a lie: for though thoſe three promiſes are all true, yet the concluſion we inferre vpon them, is altogether vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent. True it is, that though wee bee ingrafted into the eternall Vine Chriſt, yet wee retaine ſomething of the nature of the olde ſtocke whence wee were taken, which giueth to our beſt fruites an earthly taſte and ſome reliſh of the olde man. True it is, that though we are plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the beſt heauenly plants of piety, yet they grow in a forraine ſoile, and in a colde clime, farre from the Sun, and our fruites are not concocted and perfect; euen our moſt ſpirituall fruits, our prayers haue not a pleaſing taſte, vnleſſe they haue ſome ſweetning. But this defect is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by the great Angell of the couenant, who when he preſenteth theſe our fruits to God the great husbandman, addeth to them of his owne precious incenſe, which hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth their infirmity and harſhnes, and maketh them accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, <hi>Renel.</hi> 8.4. Again, true it is, that theſe our fruits, were they neuer ſo abundant, and as excellent as mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reſtored perfection can afforde, yet can they not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite thoſe crownes and kingdomes, and the eternity of that glory, but that <hi>When yee haue done all that you can, wee must ſay that yee are vnprofitable trees,</hi> not worthy the care and coſt, the feeding, the watering, the graces, the continuance beſtowed on them in this world, no more then the fruites of the Orenge and Lemmon, and Figge-trees in this our colde land are anſwerable to the extraordinary charge of their planting and maintaining; yet notwithſtanding all this, euen theſe our ſowre and vnperfect fruites, howſoeuer defectiue in themſelues, are yet ſufficiently profitable for the vſes of the Church, during this her warrefare, wherein
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25616:22"/>any meane thing is very comfortable, and troubled waters doe often ſerue for Souldiers drinke; and in that regard all they are pleaſing to the great husbandman, to ſee theſe his plants in ſome degrees profitable to the world, and by their fruits, louing, cheriſhing and feeding one another, as their roote doth feed them. But for the Crowne of heauen, and a kingdome of eternall glory, this riſeth aboue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the deſeruings of ſeruants: It paſſeth to vs by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther right and claime, by inheritance, due onely to vs as ſonnes, and therefore children and babes as ſoone as they are adopted in Chriſt: thecues and murtherers like the prodigall ſonne, vpon their faithfull return to God, though they die immediately (as the theefe on the Croſſe) before the time of fruit-bearing, and working in the Vineyarde; yet by right of this their new birth, and adoption into Chriſts body, they haue a right to heauen equal with their brethren, that haue ſpent all their life in painefull fruit bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; for <hi>if ſonnes, then heires</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>euen fellow heyres with Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> For notwithſtanding for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent whileſt theſe ſons <hi>continue in their minority, they differ not from ſeruants, though they bee Lords of all,</hi> Gal. 4.1. they obey their Fathers commandements, and they labour in his Vineyard, and doe more faithfull ſeruice in the houſe, one ſonne of loue, then twenty hyred ſeruants do for feare of ſtripes: and this is to them as diſcipline healthfull and neceſſary for their owne good alſo, and in their time of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, the foundation of their perfection in grace, to make them fit for that heauenly place, &amp; in all vertues qualified, for ſo great an inheritance in a ſociety ſo glorious. And as for the reward of ſuch obedient ſonnes, wee haue our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers anſwere to the elder brother that challenged his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers iuſtice for his bounty towards his vnthrifty ſonne, &amp; hardnes towards him who had continued moſt faithfull in his ſeruice: <hi>Sonne</hi> (ſaith our Father) <hi>thou art alwayes with mee, and all that I haue is thine:</hi> as obedient ſonnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee are alwaies with our father, this is our ſecurity,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25616:23"/>and all is ours, becauſe ſonnes. VVhat can we deſire more? Our good works and ſeruices of piety are therefore, as S. <hi>Barnard</hi> moſt excellently concludeth of them, in the very end of his Booke; <hi>De libero Arbitrio: They are the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries of our hope, the Ministeries of our loue, tokens of our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret predeſtination, foretokens of our future bleſſedneſſe: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ia regni, non cauſa regnandi: they are the way vnto our kingdom: they are not the cauſe why wee ſhall raigne as Kings.</hi> Now if notwithſtanding all this, wee Chriſtians cannot be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to exerciſe our faculties in doing good, and to bring forth fruits of loue anſwerable to our new nature, as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures do in their kind, without ſome reward and hire; behold firſt we are created, or dained, redeemed, furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with gracer, maintained in our eſtate, with bountifull ſupplies of all neceſſaries for our place: and what greater reward doth the Vine or the Oliue, or any other Creature expect for their fruits but their maintenance, euery thing in their kind; the Centurion in the Goſpell <hi>that had Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers vnder him, and could ſay to one, Come, and hee came, and to another, Goe and he went,</hi> though into certaine danger of his life; what greater rewardes could hee giue to them, then this preſent abundance and maintenance, or what greater rewards doth any ſeruant expect at his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters hand, for as great ſeruice and as faithfull as we men performe to God? Againe, were our naturall loue and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices one towards another as ready and as perfect as are the duety of one member in the body to another, (for the Apoſtle propoſeth as the ſampler of our duety) yet wee receiue a further ſufficient reward, the like mutuall helps from them againe: and what other reward doth the eye or feete, or hand expect for their daily atrendance, but the like mutuall ſeruice from the body? Againe, this is the Apoſtles counſell, Gal. 6.1. <hi>If any man bee falne, yee that are spirituall, reſtore him, conſidering thy ſelfe, leſt thou bee alſo tempted;</hi> Euen as trauellers doe mutually aid, comfort, and in any diſtreſſe releeue one another without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25616:23"/>reſpects of priuate gaine. If all this will not ſtirre vp our Chriſtian hearts to performe the duties of a Chriſtian man, by which their owne ſoules are bettered and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in grace: Behold yet a further commodity from the Maſter of the Vineyard, his ſpeciall bleſſing, and increaſe of his care and graces vpon theſe plants which are moſt fruitfull: <hi>For euery branch that beareth not fruite in mee, hee taketh away, and euery branch that beareth fruite, hee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, that it may beare more,</hi> Ioh. 15.</p>
            <p>Thus haue they increaſe of graces from heauen, &amp; which is the greateſt of all graces, the grace of perſeuerance, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other periſh they are preſerued and watered, when fruitles branches are cut off for the fire: for he not onely bleſſeth their ſtore who ſpend it vpon their brethren, as ſprings that runne are fed that they may continue; but hee dealeth mercifully alſo with them that are mercifull to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and his pitty is ready to pardon their offences, &amp; to remit their chaſticements who are kind and pittifull one to another: how gracious is our God to his vines that bring forth grapes, who hath reward for thoſe that giue but a cuppe (not of the iuyce of grapes) but of colde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to any little one for his ſake? Thus doth the tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fruits of our loue &amp; mercy make a way for vs to Chriſts mercy, and ſo to our eternall peace. Laſtly, if all this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtirre vp the graces of God in vs vnto fruitfulneſſe: Chriſts finall ſeparation &amp; triall of his ſheepe from goats, of his members from aliens and ſtrangers; his finall pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſentence of life and death giuen in the ſight of men and Angels, ſhall bee grounded, not vpon the diuerſity of their inward hidden natures, but vpon their ſeuerall kind of acts proceeding from them, vpon the ſeuerall kind of mens fruits: for <hi>euery tree is known by their fruits:</hi> all Chriſts branches yeelded grapes, all his members as they were poſſeſſed, ſo they were moued, &amp; did work by the ſpirit of loue. Hereby yee are known to be mine, if ye loue one another, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.35. and therefore this ſentence alſo is <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:25616:24"/>
            <p>our times be of any better kinde, the exact iudgement of this point belongeth vnto God; but what is in the eye, if man may iudge, whoſe tongue wil not confeſſe, but that as God ſpake of <hi>Iudah, Ezec.</hi> 16. <hi>that ſhee had iustified her elder ſiſter Samaria by her ſinnes;</hi> ſo wee haue iuſtified our eldeſt ſiſter <hi>Iudah</hi> by theſe our ſinnes, and in ſteade of grapes haue brought forth oppreſſion, vniuſtice, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, wild grapes full of poyſon, and the gall of Aſpes, our peace, our plenty, the richnes of our ſoyle in which we liue, our want of ſeuere pruning hath brought forth a luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious harueſt of peſtilent weedes in the Vineyard, which haue in a manner ouergrowne and choaked piety, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and all hearty deuotion. I know the Lord hath reſerued vnto vs a ſeede, a ſmall remnant alſo: but look on the general face of our land, how hath this hatefull ſinne of vniuſtice ouergrowne all: for the roote thereof couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſelfe-loue hath got deepe rooting, and all men now in a manner doe turne the ſappe and the bleſſings of God, their wealth, their labors, not into cluſters of fruits, according to their vocation, but into their own armes and branches, euery one ſtriueth not to bee a good, but to be a great tree, the bramble wold grow to be of the bignes of the maple, and the maple would be ſtrong and tall, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the oake, ouerdropping, and by getting ground ſtarueth another, ſome by an vnſenſible ſoaking from them, ſome by violent and open wrong, ſome vnder colour of right, &amp; pretence of loue; ſo that in euery quarter and ranke of the Lords Vineyard, there is oppreſſion, and from oppreſſion there aſcendeth a cry to the Lord of the Vineyard. But what doe I ſpeake of priuate vniuſtice betweene men and men, when there is found in our Vineyard a kinde of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, not heard of amongſt the heathen? Chriſtians in their greedineſſe to lay hands vpon their God and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and vnnaturally to ſeeke to rob him of that which the bounty of his better children had beſtowed on him for the maintenance of his worſhip amongſt men. <hi>Doth any man
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25616:24"/>rob his gods</hi> (ſayth the Lord) <hi>Malachy.</hi> 3.8. <hi>yet this people robbeth their God, and they aske wherein, euen in tythes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is one maine roote of vnnaturall impiety, a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall cauſe of all our corruption, when the branches of the Vine doe not onely ſucke and draw one from another, but doe intercept that alſo which ſhould maintaine the principall roote, on which wee all grow, euen Chriſt &amp; his ſeruice in his Church. When God ſent his ſonne vnto the Iewes; <hi>Come</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>let vs caſt him out of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard, &amp; kill him, and the inheritance ſhall be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord our life hath yet ſome inheritance and patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in his owne Vineyard amongſt vs, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his labourers, which ſhould plant Chriſt amongſt vs, and in graft vs in him, vnto his inheritance; how many couetous men doe caſt their greedy eyes, and put to their hands alſo, that firſt the Labourers might bee caſt out, and the inheritance may be theirs? What is this, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to caſt out Chriſt himſelfe out of his owne Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and as much as in vs lieth, to kill Religion and Piety, to kill Chriſt himſelfe within our hearts? For it is not the loſſe onely of earthly liuing, and the dayly diminiſhing of the maintenance of his Labourers, which is to bee lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (though when you muſſell the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out your corne, and detract from the ordinary allowance of your labouring beaſt, you ſhall find the want therof in their hartles trauell, and in your own empty har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt) but the greateſt cauſe of lamentation &amp; complaint herein, is the corruption of the Miniſtery of Chriſt, whilſt Patrones and ſuch as deale in the diſpoſing of Church li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, doe ſhut vp all the ordinary wayes for the Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to enter into the Lords Vineyard, but onely by the dore of Simonie, by which, men of good conſcience will not enter. Thus is the Lords worke and tillage of his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard vnfruitfully followed, whileſt men of corrupteſt minds, and the baſeſt of the people take vp the places of <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:25616:25"/>
            <p>ſhould bee plentifull among vs, crying, I haue looked for righteous dealing as amongſt brethren, who ſhould rather ſuffer then offer wrong, <hi>and behold a crying? I haue heard a voyce,</hi> (ſaith Moſes) <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. when hee deſcended from the Mount, the noiſe neither of them that haue the victory, nor of them that haue the worſe; for the people had ſate downe to eate, and were riſen vp to play. But where there is oppreſſion and wrong, there is a kind of warre, ſome haue the better, and ſome haue the worſe, and therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them there is alwayes heard the noiſe of them that haue the worſe; the noiſe of Oppreſſion, the noiſe of complayning and of crying. A dangerous thing to haue any crying heard in the family of God, &amp; amongſt breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren; a fearefull thing that the complaint of the oppreſſed ſhould come to his eare: <hi>Omne ſub Regno grauiore regnum eſt,</hi> Euery Court is ſubiect to a higher Court. That there ſhould be no wrongs it cannot bee prouided; but for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, there is refuge to Gods officers and miniſters of Iuſtice vpon earth, and if they by righteous iudgement do take away the cauſe of crying, God is ſatisfied: but if the wronged party can find no eaſe in thoſe inferiour Courts, but that in griefe of ſoule hee appealeth to the ſupreme Court, when hee cryeth after the Iudge of the world, as <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſalme 10. <hi>Ariſe, O Lord, lift vp thy arme, forget not the poore, wherefore doe the wicked contemne and ſay, thou wilt not regard?</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the righteous God, the refuge of the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, prouoked with thoſe often appeales, taketh iudgement into his owne hands, and as Pſalme 12. <hi>Now for the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing of the needy, and ſighes of the poore, I will riſe vp, ſayth the Lord: for ſeeing</hi> Deut. 15.9. <hi>hee chargeth vs not to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den our hearts from giuing to our wanting brother, lest he cry vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and it bee ſinne vnto vs:</hi> How much more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely will hee performe that which he proteſteth, Exod. 22. <hi>If thou trouble or vex the widdow or fatherles, &amp; ſo they call &amp; cry vnto me, I will ſurely heare their cry, and my wrath ſhal be kindled, and I will kill thee with the ſword, thy wife ſhall bee a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25616:25"/>and thy children fatherleſſe.</hi> Oh (my beloued) as there is much vniuſtice in euery eſtate, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dream the fat doe feed vpon the leane, the ſtronger vpon the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, as the fiſhes doe in the ſea: ſo let no man preſume vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the weakenes of the Plainetiffe, or vpon his own means to beare out his cauſe in the world; for though men ſhould be ſilent in their owne wrongs, the ſtones ſhall cry, and the dumbe creatures ſhall make complaint; the detained hire of the labourer, though it lie in our cheſt, yet it ſendeth vp a crie into the eares of the Lord of hoſtes, Iacob. 5. <hi>The ſtone that lyeth in the wall of our owne buildings crieth, and the beame out of the timber anſwereth, and denounceth, Woe to him that buildeth a Towne by bloud, and getteth a City by iniquity,</hi> Hab. 2.11. Who would haue thought, that when <hi>Abels</hi> mouth was ſtopped by death, and his bloud ſwallowed vp by the earth, that there had bin none to complain? but his bloud, ſaith God, Gen. 4. which the earth had ſwallowed, crieth to mee out of the bowels thereof. What a complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning noyſe then muſt the bloud of ſo many men as is dayly ſhed in this land, make in the eares of the Lord of hoaſts, crying now for vengeance againſt them that will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge it, againſt them that helpe to ſmother it, and do not remoue euill from <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will not dwel vpon theſe ſores of our land; we ſee the fruits which the choſen Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> his pleaſant plant brought forth; wee ſee the fruits which our vnthankefull land, ſo bleſſed of the Lord, ſo inſtructed in the precepts of piety and righteouſneſſe, doth affoorde to him for all his mercies and louing kindneſſes: <hi>I looked for grapes, and behold wilde grapes.</hi> Here iuſt occaſion is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to inquire out ſome reaſon, why all theſe bleſſings of God in planting, watering and pruning his Church, ſhould not be of force to make it fruitful, but that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding al his husbandry, it ſhuld ſo degenerate, &amp; bring forth the fruits not of the new, but of the old ſtocke; I wil not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to ſet down al the particular reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therof, but amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25616:26"/>many (no doubt) one, not the leaſt, is that firſt bleſſing of planting his Vineyard in a fruitfull ſoyle, his temporall bleſſings, his peace, his plenty, his furniſhing of it with all outward neceſſaries, that it might bee in heart, and ſtrong to bring forth goodly fruit. It may ſeeme ſtrange, that theſe helpes of piety ſhould proue the bane therof: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtraw is not miniſtred to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but that they are forced to wander ouer the land to ſeek ſtubble; what maruell if they yeeld not their ful tale of bricks? or if the neceſſities of this life doc diſtract <hi>Martha</hi> vnto many things; how can ſhee with her ſiſter intend to fitte at the foot of Chriſt, and by the waters of the Word which ſhould increaſe her fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe?</p>
            <p>But though <hi>Abraham, Iob, Dauid,</hi> &amp; all faithfull men truly rooted and grounded in Chriſt, the more they are increaſed with thoſe outward bleſſings of wealth, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, of authority, the more abundance of the outward fruits of righteouſneſſe and mercy they doe yeeld: yet in men not truly regenerated and altered into the nature of the roote Chriſt, of which ſort the greater parte of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſors alwayes are, lamentable experience ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, how that fatnes of the ſoyle, which in the fanctified branches of the Vine Chriſt, doth increaſe good fruit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe in theſe vnreceiued Chriſtians doth feed the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of their olde nature, and doe helpe to the fruites thereof. This corrupted the purity of the Church of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> Deut. 32.5. <hi>Hee that ſhould haue beene vpright, when hee waxed fat, spurned with his heele.</hi> And Ier. 5. <hi>Though I fedde them full, yet they committed adultery, they aſſembled themſelues by companies in harlots houſes.</hi> This corrupted the Church of Chriſtians, <hi>Religio peperit diuitias, &amp; filia deuorauit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem:</hi> Piety brought forth wealth, and this daughter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed her mother that brought her forth. This corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> As ſoone as the Church was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with riches (ſaith <hi>Platina</hi>) the worſhippers of God were turned from ſeuerity to wantonnes, and by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25616:26"/>impunity, no Prince repreſſing the lewdneſſe of men, monſters vſurped <hi>Peters</hi> ſeat.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this hath been the bane of our church, our peace, our plenty, our reſt, euen the Lords bleſsings, like plenty of ſhowers, hath brought forth this harueſt of weedes and brambles, which haue choaked true deuotion; abundance hath increaſed luxuric, and miniſtred food to the pride of life; fulneſſe of bread hath brought forth wantonnes of the fleſh, and luſt of vncleanneſſe, which in want and hunger do ordinarily wither; peace hath bread ſecurity, and called e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man to the building of his own houſe. Here beganne our gathering when wee conceiued hope of inioying, and the increaſe of our goods increaſeth our loue to wards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by ſtealing our affection ſeparateth our hearts from the roote Chriſt, in whom wee ſhould grow. And thus when men ſhould haue ſaid in their hearts; Let vs feare the Lord our God that giueth raine both earely and late, and reſerueth to vs the appointed time of harueſt; or when they ſhould ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 116. <hi>Enter into God thy reſt (O my ſoule) for he hath beene beneficiall to thee,</hi> wee ſay with the glutton, <hi>Take thy rest, O my ſoule, for thou haſt goods laid vp for many yeares, eate, drinke and be merry:</hi> Whereby as our Sauiour obiecteth to the Iewes, Math. 13.15. This peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples heart is waxen fatte, and their eares are dull of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; with their eyes haue they winked, leſt they ſhould ſee with their eyes, and heare with their eares, and vnderſtand with their hearts, and be conuerted, and I ſhould heale them. So neceſſary is the prayer of <hi>Salomon</hi> for the Church of God alſo; Giue mee not abundance, leſt I be full and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny God, and ſay, Who is the Lord?</p>
            <p>But to conclude this point, howſoeuer the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth turn this plenty of earthly bleſsings, to the nouriſhing of their earthly affections, ſeeing as Vines can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth fair &amp; goodly fruit in a barren ſoile: ſo the fruits of the Church, &amp; of righteous men cannot be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant &amp; fair without this food; ſeeing God in his mercy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25616:27"/>often taketh away this abundance, when his Church groweth wanton, &amp; by breaking the ſtaffe of bread, tryeth them with ſcarſity ſomtimes, &amp; with afflictions: the Lords challenge doth notwithſtanding ſtill continue firm: <hi>What could I haue done to my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard which I haue not done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this abundant allowance vnto our bodies, if any man thinke that the abundant prouiſion made for the foode of our ſoules alſo, this plenty of preaching and of inſtructions ſhould haue kept downe the pride of the body, and held vp the ſpirit aboue the fleſh, &amp; reformed the abuſes of wealth &amp; peace; I may adde euen this abundance of ſpiritual food, as one of the cauſes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firming &amp; hardning corrupt minds in their corruptions: for in thoſe fat hearts which are either wanton or ſleepy, the continuall plenty of the word cauſeth a fulneſſe, a luſting after Quailes and nouelties, and a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie loathing of that plaine bread of life which came from heauen: Our ſoules, ſaid the Iewes, are dried vp with this Manna. Euen as water and bread, and fire, becauſe they are things without which we cannot liue, God made them more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon then things of pleaſure, and yet becauſe they are ſo common, they are of leſſe price: ſo that word, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there is no ſpirituall life, God in his mercy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon in his church, that according to the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, it may runne like waters in the midſt of the ſtreets; and this very commonnes of it breedeth a contempt, ſo that as great noyſe and loude ſounds vnto which wee are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally accuſtomed, doe not ſtrike the eare, but rather allureth ſleepe, and as the hand which at the firſt is ſoft and tender, and galled with handy labours, doth with vſe waxe hard, and gathereth a ſenſeleſſe brawne: ſo the eares of Iewes &amp; Chriſtians, are by cuſtom not affected with the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al voice of God, &amp; their hearts, which at the firſt are tender, galled and pricked with euery hard ſentence of the word, by dayly vſe grow hard and vnſenſible; that whereas <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie</hi> repented at the hearing of one fearefull Sermon of the Prophet <hi>Ionas, Iſrael</hi> was not ſtrucken at the vſual thunder
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25616:27"/>of ſo many fearefull propheſies, neyther did the works &amp; wonders of our ſauior bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to any ſenſe of themſelus, <hi>Which if they had bin done in Tire and Sidon, nay in Sodom and Gomorrah, would haue drawn them to repentance in ſackcloth &amp; aſhes:</hi> notwithſtanding, ſeeing this word preached, is the only food, without which the ſoule pineth, and her life conſumeth: ſeeing by the ſtreams of this water, all faithfull men do grow as trees <hi>(in whole countries)</hi> planted by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſide, which bring forth their fruites in due ſeaſon: there is no reaſon why the Lord ſhould ſcant his children of this bread of ſtrength and life, becauſe ſome without gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do abuſe it to exceſſe, or that his bounty ſhould not bee magnified, in whoſe houſe the prodigall ſonne happily remembred, that euen the ſeruants haue bread inough.</p>
            <p>I come therfore to the laſt point of my Text, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the iudgement which is due to thoſe vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Vineyardes, which notwithſtanding the exceeding great means vſed for their good, doe obſtinately continue in bringing forth wilde fruites; for the Lord, the great Iudge referreth this controuerſie between himſelfe and vs, to our own conſciences, our own caſe to our owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>O inhabitants of Iudah, iudge, I pray you, betweene mee and my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard,</hi> that is, Iudge betweene your ſelues &amp; mee: for though God beginneth his iudgement at his own houſe, yet he goeth to this iudgement with a heauy hart, as it were, and a ſlow pace, though vpon our continuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations, he giueth out words of higheſt reuenge, As <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai</hi> 1.24. <hi>Ah, I. will eaſe me of my aduerſaries, and auenge mee of mine enemies;</hi> and as Hoſe. 11. <hi>The ſword ſhall fall vpon their Cities, and conſume their barres, and I will meete them as a Beare robbed of her whelpes, I will breake the kall of their hearts, I will deuoure them like a Lion, their Infants ſhall bee daſhed in peeces, and their women with child ſhall bee ripped:</hi> yet when he is to com to the execution of theſe feareful ſentences, he ſtayeth himſelfe, as in the 18. verſe of the ſame Chapter, <hi>How ſhal I giue thee vp, Ephraim? How ſhal I deliuer thee vp Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25616:28"/>How ſhall I make thee as Adamah? how ſhall I make thee as Zeboim? mine heart is turned within mee, my repentings are rowled together, I will not execute the fiercenes of my wrath, I will not returne to deſtroy Ephraim, for I am God and not man, &amp;c.</hi> which is the reaſon vvhy the Lord calleth man firſt to ſit in iudgement vpon himſelfe, becauſe as Cor. 11.13. If wee would iudge our ſelues, wee ſhould not be iudged of the Lord. <hi>Iudge therefor (I pray you) betweene mee and my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But vniuſt men that are ſo corrupt and partiall in iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging other mens cauſes, when will wee bee vpright and vncorrupt in our owne cauſes? when will a man condemne himſelfe? when will hee ſift his ſecret corners, and ſet his owne vvayes both ſeene and hidden before his own eyes? when will he vpon exact examination, giue that iuſt doom and ſentence of death vpon his owne iniquities, and vpon his owne head, making true reſtitution what lyeth in him of all his wrongs, and executing vengeance vpon al his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and corruptions, that there ſhall, bee no need of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale from his own partiall iudgement, to the iudgement ſeate of God, no need of the Lords after comming to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thoſe ſinnes, which are acknowledged, condemned, remoued and reformed? and now mercy is implored for them, and ſupplications put vp to the throne of grace: for to them, Eſai 1. <hi>Come now</hi> (ſayeth God) <hi>let vs reaſon together; If thy ſinnes were as red as crimſon, I will make them as white as ſnow, though they be double dyed as ſcarlet, I will make them like wooll.</hi> To them, that is ſpoken, <hi>Malachy</hi> 3. I will ſpare you, as a father ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerueth him.</p>
            <p>But theſe ſinnes that haue been ſo deeply rooted in vs, and by long familiarity and cuſtome, are become deare to vs, and which like that euill ſpirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.16. doe bring gain &amp; pleaſure to their maſters; there is little hope of our willing conſents to root the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out. We come like thoſe Iews with minds reſolued in our courſes, whatſoeuer the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſhall teach to the contrary: And therefore what
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25616:28"/>remaineth, but that this Vineyard ſhould expect the Lords ſentence; <hi>Now will I tell you</hi> (ſaith God) Ver. 5. <hi>what I will do?</hi> A feareful thing to fal into the hands of the liuing God.</p>
            <p>A ſentence of depriuation of his graces: A ſentence of finall deſolation, onely by remouing his mercies and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings by which onely it ſtandeth, by remouing his owne ſauing preſence from it, 1. the hedge of his defence ſhall be taken away, and then he ſhall not need to hiſſe to the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come againſt her, ſhe hath greedy enemies at home that lie in wait for the prey.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Hee will not maintaine the wall or proppes which vpholde her. How can it then but fall downe to the ground, and bee trampled on by the feet of euery wilde beaſt?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He wil not beſtow dreſſing and pruning of her by diſcipline and chaſticements: how can ſhee then but grow wilde? Shee ſhall not be digged and weeded; then will thornes and corruptions ouergrow her. And yet by all theſe puniſhments the wrath of the Lord is not appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for there remaineth one, which taketh avvay all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hopes and poſsible meanes of any one branch to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, and liue in the middeſt of theſe former deſolations: Hee will commaund the cloudes, that they raine no raine vpon her: How then can the drie and barren earth bring forth any good?</p>
            <p>I cannot, I need not proſecute the particulars of this ſentence: wee all know how exactly and ſeuerely it is long ſince executed vpon the Vineyard of Iſrael, and not a word of the Lord is fallen to the ground: that Garden and Paradiſe of the earth, that delightfull habitation of the mighty God of Iſrael, wherein the light of life ſhined, when all the earth beſides was darkeneſſe, lyeth now as waſte, as the wilderneſſe of <hi>Horeb;</hi> and where the voice of the Bridegroome vvas heard, and of him that did leade the dance vvith Tabrets and Harpes; vvhere the people of God ioyned together in the ioyfull ſongs of <hi>Sion;</hi> there
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25616:29"/>now <hi>Zims</hi> and Satyres dance, the Oſtrich &amp; the Shrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owle doe dwell there, and the inhabitants themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt out of their Cities and Vineyards, and ſcattered ouer the whole earth amongſt them that hate them, doe liue vvithout GOD, vvithout a Sauiour and Protector, vvithout a ſacrifice, vvithout hope and comfort, a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne Nation, &amp; according to the Propheſies, the reproch and hiſsing and ſcorne of all people, a perpetuall exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry monument in the middeſt of Chriſtians and Nations of all tongues, of the Lords iuſtice vpon his owne vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Church and family.</p>
            <p>Concerning novv our ſelues, vvho haue ſucceeded the Ievves in Gods inheritance, and are made a parte of his Vineyard, vvhat can vvee alledge for our ſelues, why the ſame ſentence ſhould not paſſe vpon vs? If vve compare Gods mercies towards vs, vvee goe beyond the Ievves, as farre as the light of Chriſt and his Apoſtles doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the light of <hi>Moſes</hi> and his Prophets, and the ſonne of righteouſnes doth goe beyond the Starres of the night, the grace of the Goſpel beyond the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of the law. If vve compare our fruits of thankefulneſſe, what one complaint doe the Prophets make of the Ievves co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, vniuſtice, oppreſsion, vvantonneſſe and pride, vvhich is not, by altering the names, as it vvere, ſpoken to our land, beſides the ſinnes of ſacrilege, of glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony proper to vs?</p>
            <p>VVherfore ſeeing where the Lord had iuſter cauſe to expect ſuch multitude of grapes, hee is prouoked vvith a continual Vintage of theſe vvild grapes, I wil not dare to pronounce the LORDS ſentence, that thus and thus vvill hee doe vnto his Vineyard.</p>
            <p>Yet ſeeing GOD referreth it to our iudgements, to pronounce vvhat it hath deſerued; I may vvith the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret aſſent of your ovvne conſciences affirme, that, in that hee hath not yet executed that ſentence vpon vs, hee hath not dealt vvith vs after our ſins, neyther revvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25616:29"/>vs according to our iniquities: for the hedge of Iewrie is broken downe, and the wilde Bore hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that Vine. The Beaſts of the field haue deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it vp. But the LORD hath kept our hedges, and the Bore hath not deuoured, the wild beaſtes haue not broken in vpon vs. The LORDS finall Seſsions are approching; and who knoweth whether by his exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarie iuſtice, hee being ſufficiently knowne to the world? Theſe publike &amp; corporal executions of his wrath vpon ſinnefull Nations, bee not referred vnto that day. This is our chiefeſt cauſe of feare, leſt a ſpirituall curſe proceede out of his mouth againſt vs, like that of our Sauiour Chriſt vpon the barren figge-tree; leſt he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to prune and dreſſe this his Vineyard; leſt hee neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to weede out our thornes, and ſuffer the brambles to choke that little good that is found amongſt vs; leſt to our finall deſolation and ſpirituall vaſtity, hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the cloudes not to raine their raine vpon vs leſt hee make the Heauen ouer our heades to bee as braſſe: for then the earth ſhall bee as yron, or as drie and fruitleſſe duſt.</p>
            <p>What fruite can earth yeeld, when it is forſaken of heauenly grace?</p>
            <p>Oh ſtirre vp therefore the graces of GOD which are in you, and apply them vnto fruitfulneſſe; that yee may yet take, and lade the Altar of the LORDS wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe with the ſacrifice of your fruites. Say in your hearts, as the Vine, Iudg. 9. <hi>Should I leaue my Wine, whereby I cheare both God and man, and goe to aduance my ſelfe aboue other trees?</hi> That as, Eſai 65. <hi>When there is wine found in the cluſter, one doth ſay, Destroy it not, for there is a bleſsing in it:</hi> So our Lord viſiting this Vineyard, may haue cauſe to ſay, <hi>There are clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters found in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine, deſtroy it not, for there is a bleſſing in it: and a bleſſing be vpon it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, and thus onely may wee continue Chriſt the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25616:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>Vine vnto our land, &amp; our ſelues a Vineyard vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt; A Seate of perpetuity for the Lords mercies, and inheritance of life to our Children and Poſterity. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25616:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
